{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A minister with this surname withdrew his support for the Salem witch trials after his wife, Sarah, was accused. Another man with this surname wrote about the effects of treason accusations on Philip Nolan in A Man Without a Country. Another man with this surname was captured at Flushing Bay following the Battle of Long Island. That man said “I only regret that I have but one life to lose for my country.” For ten points, give this surname of the Revolutionary War spy, Nathan.",
      "answer": "Hale A"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man flayed his daughter’s lovers after accusations of adultery in the Nesle’s Tower affair. This man’s claims to supremacy were repudiated in the Unam sanctam, prompting him to send Guillaume de Nogaret to arrest Boniface VIII. This king burned Jacques de Molay at the stake in an attempt to curb the power of the Knights Templar. Clement V was elected pope during this man’s reign, beginning the Avignon papacy. For ten points, name this French king named for his handsomeness.",
      "answer": [
        "Philip IV",
        "Philip the Fair"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Charles Moose resigned as a leading investigator into this event after his police department banned himRfrom making a book deal about it titled Three Weeks in October. A stolen Bushmaster XM-15 was used in these attacks, which resulted in a death sentence for John Allen Muhammad. Lee Boyd Malvo was a juvenile perpetrator of this event, whose first victim was shot in Rockville, Maryland. For ten points, name these 2002 attacks that affected the metropolitan area of the U.S. capital.",
      "answer": [
        "Washington D.C. sniper attacks",
        "Beltway sniper,",
        "District of Columbia sniper attacks"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "ThispersondefendedassassinLeonCzolgosz[CHOW-gaw]asa“supersensitivebeing.”Thelasttwelve Dchapters of a work by this author about the Kronstadt Rebellion were removed entirely by Doubleday, Page & Co., resulting in her book My Further Disillusionment in Russia. In response to World War One, this editor of the journal Mother Earth co-founded the No Conscription League with Alexander Berkman who tried to assassinate Henry Clay Frick. For ten points, name this Lithuanian-born anarchist.",
      "answer": "Emma Goldman"
    },
    {
      "question": "KKK activities in this state were the target of the FBI’s COINTELPRO-WHITE HATE program. In this state, three CORE workers were found dead under a dam. In 1964, delegates from this state to the Democratic National Convention created this state’s namesake Freedom Democratic Party. A riot broke out in Oxford after James Meredith attempted to enroll at this state’s namesake university. Freedom Summer occurred in, for ten points, what state that was described as “burning” during the Civil Rights Movement?",
      "answer": "Mississippi T"
    },
    {
      "question": "This empire was splintered into the Joma and Hamana spheres shortly after its final ruler, Mahmud IV, was defeated at the Battle of Djenne. Another ruler of this empire allegedly founded it after using a rooster-tipped arrow at the battle of Kirina to defeat Sumanguru. Sundiata Keita ruled this empire, another ruler of which allegedly inflated the price of gold along the Mediterranean after his lavish spending F while on the hajj. Mansa Musa was a ruler of, for ten points, what West African empire?",
      "answer": [
        "Mali Empire",
        "Manden Kurufaba,",
        "Nyeni"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "While serving as a self described, “oppressed assistant professor,” this man wrote an essay about calculating interest rates for goods traveling at light speeds. This economist argued that there were parallels in economic policy between 2008 and 1929 in The Return of Depression Economics. This winner of the 2008 Nobel Prize in Economics described U.S. foreign policies in The Great Unravelling. For ten A points, name this economist and columnist for the New York Times.",
      "answer": "Paul Krugman"
    },
    {
      "question": "A three-day retreat to this location, known as the Alberich Maneuver, was cited in propaganda as “Hun barbarism.” A decision to create this position “was not reached without a painful struggle,” according to Erich Ludendorff, who started building it after the Battle of the Somme. The Siegfried Line was one section of, for ten points, what system of artillery, blockhouses, and trenches built during World War One, named for a Field Marshal who later became the German president? R",
      "answer": [
        "Hindenburg Line",
        "“Position” in place of “Line,”",
        "Siegfriedstellung",
        "Siegfried Line/Position before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Alberta’s Newbrook Observatory was the first to photograph this object whose sighting was an initial goal of Operation Moonwatch. Sergei Korolev proposed the original plan for developing this object, and its prototype, “Object D,” was deemed too complicated to meet the early-1957 deadline. This object’s three week mission was a major blow to the U.S. in the Space Race. For ten points, name this Soviet artificial satellite, the first ever launched into space. D",
      "answer": "Sputnik 1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Larry McDonald attempted to impeach an African-American holder of this position. The first woman to hold this position defended anti-communist dictatorships in her namesake doctrine. One holder of this position was ready to wait for an answer to a question he posed to Valerian Zorin “until Hell freezes over.” A woman who was initially hesitant to label the Hutu-Tutsi conflict as a genocide held this post. For ten points, name this position held by Andrew Young and Madeleine Albright.",
      "answer": "United States Ambassador to the United Nations T"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A no-confidence vote against this politician failed despite its support from Herbert Hupka. This politician was popular with the student-led APO, Fwho had grown dissatisfied with his conservative predecessor Kurt Kiesinger. This politician resigned after his aide, Gunter Guillaume, was exposed as a Stasi spy. This leader signed the Basic Treaty, which began to normalize relations with an eastern neighbor. For ten points, name this West German chancellor who proposed the conciliatory Ostpolitik.",
        "answer": [
          "Willy Brandt",
          "Herbert Frahm"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1990, Willy Brandt went to this Middle Eastern city and secured the release of 174 Western hostages, less than two months before the U.S. and its allies launched attacks on the country of which this city is the capital. A",
        "answer": "Baghdad, Iraq"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At a meeting in this state, John Cotton Smith claimed that its central group had to deal with “a formidable and exasperated enemy.” A group of Massachusetts attendees to a meeting in this state was known as the Essex Junto. Timothy Pickering attended a meeting in this state that called for an end to a concept that was believed to favor the Jeffersonian Democratic-Republicans, the three-fifths compromise. For ten points, name this state that hosted the Federalists at the Hartford Convention. R",
        "answer": "Connecticut"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One proposed amendment to come out of Hartford would have required the U.S. president to be from a different state than their predecessor. This was intended to break the “dynasty” of this state from which four of the first five presidents hailed.",
        "answer": "Commonwealth of Virginia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s first project was an adaptation of farces by the Roman playwright, Plautus. This man D won a Pulitzer Prize for a work that revolves around a fictionalized version of Georges Seurat. In 2004, a production by this man won five Tony Awards and starred Neil Patrick Harris as Lee Harvey Oswald. For ten points, name this creator of A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum, Sunday in the Park with George, and Assassins.",
        "answer": "Stephen Sondheim"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Sondheim work has won five Tony Awards, had an Oscar-nominated film version starring James Corden, and intertwines the plots of classic fairy tales by the Brothers Grimm and Charles Perrault.",
        "answer": "Into the Woods T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Almost four minutes of the film The President’s Last Band depicting this man were censored after his son sued. This man faced the Bu-Ma riots and passed the Yushin Constitution. This man’s friend, Kim Jae-gyu, the head of the Korean CIA, assassinated this man in 1979. Unit 124 tried to kill this man in the Blue House Raid. The “Miracle on the Han River” was led by, for ten points, what president of South F Korea whose daughter, also a president of South Korea, is now in jail for bribery?",
        "answer": "Park Chung-hee"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of Park’s initiatives that promoted literacy in South Korea was the abolishment of hanja, meaning that hangul was to be used exclusively. What is hangul?",
        "answer": [
          "Korean alphabet",
          "answers indicating Korean letters",
          "writing system A"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Tupac Shakur mourned this woman in his song “Hellrazor,” stating that she “never got to see the bullet, just heard the shot.” An Ice Cube song that includes the line “So pay respect to the black fist / Or we’ll burn your store right down to a crisp” was inspired by the murder of this woman who allegedly stole a bottle of orange juice. The song “Black Korea” was inspired by the death of, for ten points, what 15-year-old girl who was murdered by Soon Ja Du in the buildup to the Rodney King riots?",
        "answer": "Latasha Harlins"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "John Singleton became the youngest person and the first African-American nominated for an AcaRdemy Award for Best Director for this 1991 film whose soundtrack includes Ice Cube’s “How to Survive in South Central.”",
        "answer": "Boyz n the Hood"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While entering Naples, this man was given Bernini’s Boy with a Dragon. Charters giving power to regions of Aragon were taken away by this king’s Nueva Planta decrees. This man’s rule was broken into two by the seven-month reign of Louis I. Louis XIV declared that if the Petit Dauphin, Louis, died this man would have to surrender the throne, leading to the War of the Spanish Succession. For ten points, D name this successor to Charles II, the first Bourbon king of Spain.",
        "answer": [
          "Philip V",
          "Felipe V"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The death of Charles II of Spain ended the nearly 200-year Spanish reign of this family that began with Charles I, the grandson of Holy Roman Emperor Maximilian I.",
        "answer": "Habsburg T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While fighting the Amorites, this man commanded the sun and moon to stand still in the sky. Along with Caleb, this son of Nun was the only one of the spies to support invading Canaan. Modern scholarship suggests that this man’s namesake book is not historically accurate but rather is meant to detail obedience to the law. For ten points, name this successor of Moses, the Biblical leader of the Hebrews at the F legendary Battle of Jericho.",
        "answer": [
          "Joshua",
          "Jehoshua,",
          "Hoshea"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "According to the Bible, Joshua was born in this country during the Hebrew exile and prior to the Exodus from this country.",
        "answer": "Egypt A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle nearly turned thanks to a a woody 600-yard gap undefended by the men of James Lane and James Archer. An offensive, prompted by this battle’s result, became bogged down in heavy winter rains and was subsequently called the Mud March. This battle hinged upon James Longstreet’s defense of a stone wall. For ten points, name this battle of late 1862 in which Robert E. Lee thwarted a Union attempt to cross the Rappahannock.",
        "answer": "Battle of Fredericksburg"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the defeat at Fredericksburg, Joseph Hooker was made commander of this force, the prinRcipal Union Army in the Eastern Theater.",
        "answer": "Army of the Potomac"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Mexican-American War",
      "prompt": "During the Mexican-American War who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "State whose annexation and admission to the US preceded the war in 1845 F",
          "answer": "Texas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty that ended the war",
          "answer": "Treaty of Guadalupe-Hidalgo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Peninsula blockaded by the U.S. Navy’s Pacific Squadrom",
          "answer": "Baja California A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Future president who won battles at Monterrey and Buena Vista",
          "answer": "Zachary Taylor"
        },
        {
          "question": "Proposed American law to ban slavery in any territory acquired from Mexico",
          "answer": "Wilmot Proviso"
        },
        {
          "question": "Request made by Abraham Lincoln for the exact locations upon which blood had spilt",
          "answer": "Spot Resolutions R"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group of mostly immigrant soldiers who defected to the Mexican army",
          "answer": [
            "St. Patrick’s Batallion",
            "Foreign Legion of Patricios"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "American diplomat who secured a peace treaty but was fired after ignoring his recall to the US",
          "answer": "Nicholas Trist D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "First Battle of the Marne",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city which a Franco-British victory saved from a German attack F",
          "answer": "Paris"
        },
        {
          "question": "Style of positional warfare that followed it and thereafter defined the Western Front",
          "answer": "Trench warfare"
        },
        {
          "question": "German plan for the invasion of France that it thwarted",
          "answer": "Schlieffen Plan A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Transportation method that Joseph Gallieni used to transport reserve troops",
          "answer": "Taxicabs"
        },
        {
          "question": "Campaign of which it was a part, named for the efforts of the opposing armies to envelop each other’s northern flanks",
          "answer": "Race to the Sea"
        },
        {
          "question": "French commander-in-chief who reconcentrated his armies to win the battle R",
          "answer": "Joseph “Papa” Joffre"
        },
        {
          "question": "German Chief of the General Staff who sent reinforcements to East Prussia",
          "answer": "Helmuth von Moltke, the Younger"
        },
        {
          "question": "French commander of the Sixth Army whose attack opened a gap between the two German field armies",
          "answer": "Michel-Joseph Maunoury D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Liberia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital named after the 5th U.S. President F",
          "answer": "Monrovia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Neighboring country governed from Freetown that clashed with the Armed Forces of Liberia in the 1980s",
          "answer": "Republic of Sierra Leone"
        },
        {
          "question": "Precious minerals from a war zone that Liberia mined for and exported through Cote d’Ivoire A",
          "answer": [
            "Blood diamonds",
            "Conflict diamonds"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Organization founded by Robert Finley that sent freed slaves to live in Liberia",
          "answer": "American Colonization Society"
        },
        {
          "question": "First elected African female head of state who served as Liberia’s president from 2006 to 2018",
          "answer": "Ellen Johnson Sirleaf 6RFormer Liberian warlord who was found guilty of aiding war crimes in 2012 ANSWER: Charles Taylor"
        },
        {
          "question": "President of Liberia who was executed on live television by Prince Johnson",
          "answer": "Samuel Doe"
        },
        {
          "question": "2011 Nobel Peace Prize winner who led the Women of Liberia Mass Action for Peace movement",
          "answer": "Leymah Gbowee D T"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During a speech at West Point, this man controversially said, “Great Britain has lost an empire and has not yet found a role.” This maFn won the 1970 Pulitzer Prize for History for his memoir of his time serving in his highest post titled (20 pts)",
        "Present at the Creation. This Secretary of State’s tenure during the Communist Party’s expulsion of the Kuomintang led critics to blame him for the “loss of China.” The formation of (10 pts)",
        "NATO occurred during this man’s tenure and he helped outline a president’s doctrine providing financial aid to opponents of communism. For ten points, name this Secretary of State under Truman."
      ],
      "answer": "Dean Acheson A"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this battle, Auguste de Caulaincourt was killed in a cavalry charge against the Raevsky Redoubt which absorbed much of the French assault during this battle. The (20 pts)",
        "Bagration [buh-gruh-tee-ON] fleches were a system of fortifications created for this battle by the namesake Georgian prince who was killed during it. The winning commander’s refusal to commit the (10 pts)",
        "Imperial Guard in this battle is considered by some historians to have thrown away his victory. For ten points, name this 1812 engagement outside Moscow, the climactic battle of Napoleon’s invasion of Russia."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Borodino R"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These men are depicted as incredibly tall next to picketers in a mosaic at Syracuse University. These two men rest in coffins in a painting which depicts Judge Webster (20 pts)",
        "Thayer taking an oath in a portrait in the background. “The Passion” of these two men is the subject of a Ben Shahn painting. A series of ballads to these men, including “Two Good Men” and “You Souls of (10 pts)",
        "Boston,” was written by Woody Guthrie. Convicted of the murder of Alessandro Berardelli and Frederick Parmenter, for ten points, name these two Italian anarchists executed in 1927. DANSWER: Nicola Sacco and Bartolomeo Vanzetti (4) Stuart Goldman’s best-selling book focuses on this battle and its effects on World War Two. Grievances from the Changkufeng Incident a year before this battle were a leading cause of it. The first mass-scale use of (+) airpower for a military purpose is sometimes cited as this battle’s Nomonhan Incident. Georgy Zhukov came to prominence at this battle that arose after disputes concerning whether the namesake river dividing (*) Manchuria and Mongolia constituted an international boundary. For ten points, name this 1939 battle along the border of the Soviet Union and Japan."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battles of Khalkhin Gol",
        "Battle of Nomonhan",
        "Nomonhan Incident before mentioned T"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A character from this city dreams of owning a video store and sells stolen refrigerators to raise money. Memphis Lee demands 10,000 dollars to sell his restaurant in the play Two Trains Running which is set in this city’s (20 pts)",
        "Hill District. Another character from this city notes that “Jackie Robinson wasn’t nobody.” That character, Troy Maxson, is barred from F driving this city’s garbage trucks in the play (10 pts)",
        "Fences. For ten points, name this city, the setting of a namesake cycle of plays by August Wilson intended to describe the Black experience in 20th century America."
      ],
      "answer": "Pittsburgh"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man, whose appointment to West Point was legendarily secured by Abraham Lincoln, fled to Canada after worrying that his execution of twenty-two men after the Battle A of New Bern might be seen as a war crime. This man and two cavalry commanders were reportedly having a fish fry when the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Five Forks broke out. Lewis Armistead died while commanding a brigade under this general who reportedly told Robert E. Lee, “I have (10 pts)",
        "no division” after a disastrous attack on Cemetery Ridge. For ten points, name this Confederate general who led his namesake charge at the Battle of Gettysburg."
      ],
      "answer": "George Pickett"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) According to Josephus, Herod the Great captured this city and built a fortress on its plaRteau. Inhabitants of this city allegedly set everything but food stockpiles on fire to show that they had the means to choose survival. This city, to which the (20 pts)",
        "narrow Snake Path led, was taken by Lucius Silva’s Fretensis legion after a ramp was constructed in order to allow for the use of a siege tower. After Roman troops succeeded in capturing this location, a large number of Sicarii rebels from the (10 pts)",
        "Zealot faction committed suicide. For ten points, name this heavily defended Jewish fortress atop a large hilltop in Israel."
      ],
      "answer": "Masada D"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of this man’s successors as consul, Quintus Fabius Vibulanus, was named by Appius Claudius as part of the second set of decemviri. This man unsuccessfully summoned the plebeian Spurius (20 pts)",
        "Maelius, leading Gaius Servius Ahala to kill Maelius. This man’s behavior after defeating the Aequi at the Battle of Mount Algidus inspired Henry Knox to name a (10 pts)",
        "society after him to assist the families of Continental Army soldiers and sailors. For ten points, name this virtuous Roman farmer and statesman who twice relinquished his dictatorial power once threats to Rome were vanquished."
      ],
      "answer": "Lucius Quinctius Cincinnatus T"
    }
  ]
}